The Apothecary Diaries
This story is a work of fiction. The names of all of the characters, organizations, and so on
are imaginary. It also bears no connection to any specific real-life events.
Episode 2: Chilly Apothecary
Hey!
It's poison!
Damn you! Who's behind this?!
Wait.
Tend to the soldiers first.
Poison?
The food was cooked by the villagers.
The village leader has been put into
custody for aiding the barbarians.
Please advise.
Understood. Give me a moment.
As you wish.
By the way...
I heard you hired a new lady-in-waiting
to serve Concubine Gyokuyou.
Yes. Concubine Gyokuyou
has only four women serving her.
It's too few compared to Concubine Lihua,
who also high-ranking and has over ten.
It hurts her dignity as
a high-ranking concubine.
Yes. However, Concubine Gyokuyou
is not just bright and gentle,
but also wise and cautious.
She would never hire
someone of unknown origin.
Being constantly wary of
everyone around them
is the only way an emperor's
concubine can survive.
And who is this new lady-in-waiting?
Gaoshun, I found just the right pawn.
It's that freckled servant girl.
Her knowledge of medicine
is too valuable to pass up.
I see. But if she were to abuse
that knowledge...
I'll make sure she can't do that.
It should be easy.
I suppose I should seduce
her a little, just in case.
It's so cool that you get to serve
a high-ranking concubine.
Ugh, I really didn't want to.
Apothecary. Are you ready to move?
Yes, I'm on my way to the Jade Pavilion soon.
Did you need something?
No, nothing.
Huh?
Why's he here, then? Nothing better to do?
Be sure to serve Concubine Gyokuyou well.
Excuse me.
Good luck, Maomao!
Ew, gross...
Are you Maomao?
Oh, yes.
I am Hongniang,
head lady-in-waiting for Lady Gyokuyou.
For starters, I'll show you around
the Jade Pavilion. Follow me.
Yes.
Welcome to the Jade Pavilion.
I've been waiting for you, Maomao.
Looks like Xiaoling is happy to see you, too.
We're glad to have you around.
Thank you.
This is the parlor, where we bring guests.
So big...
This is the kitchen. You should be able
to do some simple cooking here.
Wow.
This is the living room.
Here are the other ladies-in-waiting.
Let me introduce them to you.
Everyone, gather up.
Yes!
Nice to meet you, I'm Yinghua. Ask me anything!
I am Guiyuan. Nice to meet you.
I am Ailan. Very pleased to meet you.
I'm Maomao. Looking forward
to working with you.
At the Jade Pavilion,
we don't hire any serving girls.
So, we do all the work around here.
It's the least we can do to make sure
Lady Gyokuyou lives comfortably.
Then I'll also—
You go ahead and rest in your room.
Huh?
Take it easy.
You have a special task coming up.
Special task?
Maomao, I'll show you to your room.
Um, sure.
Did you see her left arm?
She's hiding it with those bandages,
but there are scars under them, right?
She must have been abused
by her parents back home,
and sold off to the rear palace...
On top of that, there's that terrible job...
That poor, unfortunate girl!
Wait here until you're summoned, all right?
Hey, um...
I've gotten quite the promotion.
The Jade Pavilion's always
been run by a select elite.
So of course a newcomer
wouldn't be totally welcome.
But they all looked so...
Sympathetic? Why?
Tasting for poison.
That's your job, apothecary.
Poison! Tasting for poison!
Oops.
Food cooked for the concubine changes hands
a few times before being brought here.
It's possible for it to be
poisoned during that process.
In fact, when Concubine Gyokuyou
became pregnant,
her food was poisoned at least twice.
The taster back then received nerve damage
and still can't move her hands or feet.
I see. That's why the others
were sympathetic to me.
So... Here you go.
These bowls...
No suspicious colors. Or scents.
No numbness.
I can't detect any poison here.
Back when I lived by the brothels,
I ran a lot of experiments on my arm.
Mad scientist.
I've gradually trained my body against poisons,
so many of them have no effect on me.
To be honest, detecting
poison isn't suited for me.
But in a way, I'm lucky to get this job.
She's laughing...
I think you should switch to silver plates.
Those react to poisons.
It's like Master Jinshi said. We used
ceramics on purpose to test you.
That was his idea!
Your knowledge applies to both
poisons and medicines, then.
I used to work as an apothecary.
If you'd mentioned that you're literate,
you would have gotten paid more.
I was kidnapped and brought here,
and I'm incensed that part of my pay
gets sent to the kidnappers.
So, you'd rather take less pay than give
your kidnappers drinking money, hmm?
Goodness, this was quite expensive.
You couldn't afford it with
your lady-in-waiting salary.
How will you send money to your family?
In fact, we might need to charge them.
Ah, I'm so sorry.
Please take it out of the money to my family.
If that's not enough,
from my savings, too.
Yes, I'll arrange the paperwork.
By the way, here's hazard pay
for your food tasting services.
Almost equal to my regular salary...
Since the kidnappers don't get
a cut of this, it all goes to me.
Thank you.
She knows how to motivate her workers.
Don't worry about it!
Rest for now.
We've always been fully staffed.
I'm bored!
I only get called on as taster for
two meals and the mid-day tea time.
Now that I have my own room,
if there was a venomous snake or
something, I could experiment...
Maomao.
Did you need me, Lady Gyokuyou?
He does, actually.
Ugh.
Why won't this work on her?
How may I serve you today?
I received these from a certain
military officer. Can you taste them?
Baozi buns...
It has an aphrodisiac in it.
You can tell without eating it?
It's not harmful. Please
feel free to enjoy them.
Given who I received
these from, I can't do that.
Perhaps that person
might visit you tonight.
Hmm. So you can tell by the smell alone?
Did this guy try to make me eat one
knowing they have an aphrodisiac in them?!
I had one more question for you.
Yes, what is it?
A squad of soldiers on a mission to attack
some barbarians was poisoned the other day.
Poisoned?
Yes. Several fell ill after a meal.
They reported nausea, difficulty
breathing, and other ailments.
Nausea and difficulty breathing...
The meal was prepared in a nearby village.
They arrested the village leader
for assisting the barbarians,
but an officer diffused the situation,
and has put the decision on hold.
It would be natural to assume
the villagers poisoned the soldiers, but...
Master Jinshi, where were they eating?
They were at camp, so
they likely ate outside.
Did the villagers provide
the plates and chopsticks?
No, the soldiers should
have provided their own.
Did you notice something?
This is just my opinion.
Let me share something.
This flower is a rhododendron.
Does it taste good?
No, eating it causes nausea
and difficulty breathing.
Hey!
As you see, even the rear palace
has plants with poison in them.
This one has poison in the leaves, but some
have poison in the branches or roots.
Some wood can even emit poison when burned.
When burned...?
I see.
It's fortunate the bright
officer was there.
We could have lost a whole village.
Yes.
If that's all, I'll take my leave.
No, wait.
Is there more?
Can you make an aphrodisiac?
Make? You mean...
Making drugs?!
Given time, the proper ingredients,
and the right tools,
I could make something like that.
Master Jinshi, where are you headed?
I'm returning to my office. May I help you?
I was wondering if you'd have
tea with me in my room...
Unfortunately, I have much work
to attend to. Please excuse me.
The servants must not be aware
that Master Jinshi serves as a test
of their loyalty to the emperor.
Just because the emperor does not visit her,
she shouldn't try and lure
other men to her room.
What an indiscretion.
Indeed.
A concubine cannot simply be
beautiful or well-educated.
They must be loyal to
the emperor, and be chaste.
But to place you in the rear palace
and use your beauty as a test...
Our emperor can be quite severe at times.
We all use whatever is available to us. But...
Not only does she feel no lust
for me, but that look...
Glare...
I've never been so harshly
looked down on in my life.
Well then, I will take my leave.
Perhaps that person
might visit you tonight.
Tonight... Tonight...
I'm leaving now.
Good luck.
Yes!
Pardon me.
The quack doctor, and...
Miss Maomao. Let me reintroduce myself.
I am Gaoshun.
I'm Master Jinshi's assistant.
Pleased to make your acquaintance.
Hello.
It can't be easy assisting that guy.
What is this servant girl
doing in my territory?
This way, please.
I have been told you may use
anything in this room.
Is that some sort of cursed dance?
What a luxury, being able
to use paper so freely.
And also, I need...
Over there?
He's really quick to notice things.
Compared to his master...
If you're not going to do
anything, just go away.
Here you are.
Thank you.
That's not enough...
What is this?
It's cacao.
If you need more, we'll simply find more.
But it's from the West,
and the far southern region, too.
I'm sure there's more in
the trading goods storage.
Milk, butter, sugar, honey,
and powdered cacao.
That should be enough.
All expensive ingredients.
I wonder what she's making?
A snack, maybe?
What are you all doing?
Get back to work!
We're sorry!
Goodness.
Now to actually make the aphrodisiac!
I had a taste of cacao just once in the past.
This is called "chocolate." Say "ah," Maomao.
Maomao?!
Perhaps a malicious customer wanted to get
a popular courtesan's attention.
Unfortunately for him, he got
banned by the shrewd old lady.
Looks good.
There.
Now I just cool it and wait for it to harden.
I have a bit left over. Oh, I know.
This probably doesn't need to be cooled.
I guess I should clean up now.
Wait, medicinal herbs?!
There too?! And over there!
Oops, I got a little carried away.
Sorry for the delay!
At least we know it works.
So, what's going on?!
Well, it is what it is...
It's fine, they didn't go all the way—Ow!
So, this is the aphrodisiac?
No, this is.
Then what are the other ones?
A midnight snack for myself.
If you're used to alcohol
and other stimulants,
it won't have that much of an effect.
Oh, so it won't be a problem if I ate it?
Please don't do that!
Haha, just joking.
What a reprehensible joke to make
in front of the emperor's concubine.
But if he approached someone with
an impassioned blush on that face...
It'd immediately captivate
any person, male or female.
He does have a great face, after all.
It's quite strong, so please
limit it to one piece at a time.
Too many could excessively increase
blood flow and cause nosebleeds.
Maybe you can make some for the emperor,
to avoid things getting too dull.
It should be around three times
more potent than the usual tonic.
Three times? Does she mean duration...?
Let's pretend I didn't hear that.
Also, please only use it when you are
alone with the person in mind.
Three times... Three times...
I see.
Well, I'll take my leave now.
So she can make drugs?
How reliable.
It's finally over.
Good work.
Thank you.
I see.
I hope there aren't any victims.
Next Time
Next time: "The Unsettling
Matter of the Spirit."
Episode 3: The Unsettling Matter of the Spirit