Are you serious?
So, what would you do?
After all, you're the gardener
maintaining my flower garden.
He truly is cunning.
How ironic.
No matter how hard I try,
both in intellect and martial arts,
I can only slightly
outperform a regular person.
Instead, I am granted an appearance
more beautiful than anyone.
The things I truly want
are so far out of reach.
I was dissatisfied at first,
but I've gotten over it.
My sweet gaze, my sweet voice...
I'll use my superior tools to my advantage.
I'm aware that ultimately, I'm just a child
floundering on the emperor's palm.
As you wish.
I'll manage his rear palace,
or whatever else he wants.
That's the only way I can choose my own path.
The Apothecary Diaries
Verdigris House
This story is a work of fiction. The names of all of the characters, organizations, and so on
are imaginary. It also bears no connection to any specific real-life events.
I don't need this much, Big Sis.
Sure, sure. Take this, this... Oh! And this, too.
Episode 13: Serving in the Outer Court
I'm not going to be using lipstick.
What do you mean? Can't you put in
the least bit of effort to look proper?
Only courtesans have to get
prettied up to go to work.
I want to work with herbs...
Ow!
You've landed such a nice job at the palace!
And you're telling me you can't dress up
appropriately for the position?
You have to be thankful
for that every day.
Otherwise, you'll lose your great customers.
Meimei is really convincing.
She's old enough to start considering
retirement as a courtesan,
but her popularity hasn't waned at all,
because she has the intellect
to entertain her customers
through song, chess, and go.
Maomao.
Wow, what a huge package.
Pairin, Joka.
I'm glad you found a good
workplace. Go make a fortune.
Got it.
If you could bring back some paying
customers, that would be great too!
Find some good, rich guys.
Someone with vigor, pretty please!
Uh, yeah...
Verdigris House
My new workplace... Or should I say,
the workplace I'm returning to,
is the area in the palace
called the rear palace.
It's a garden of women who are there
to have children for the emperor.
I was supposed to work here
as a lowly servant girl, but...
You with the freckles, stay here
I solved the mystery of the dying
infant heirs, which drew attention.
I was promoted to lady-in-waiting
for Lady Gyokuyou,
then got sucked into various
troubles as a food taster.
After that, a bunch of stuff happened,
leading to me getting fired.
Who would've thought I'd be back again?
I succumbed to the allure
of the caterpillar fungus,
but looking back, that might
have been careless of me.
Of course, seen from the outside,
it's a huge lucky break.
I do have some reservations about leaving
my dad behind to go live elsewhere for work,
but the rules are a lot less strict this time,
and I'm not treated as missing anymore.
Dad also said I should do as I like, but...
What did he mean by that, I wonder?
I'm home.
They loaded you up, didn't they?
What should I do? I definitely need
my mortar and pestle, and my notebook.
I can't bring less underwear—
Maomao, you probably can't take those with you.
Huh?
You're not a doctor.
Having such things would make you appear
like you're plotting a poisoning.
Come now, don't make that face.
It was your decision to go.
You can't back out now.
Really?
You should be able to gradually get
permission to bring more things in.
Get ready and go to sleep.
Tomorrow is your first day.
Fine...
Well, you haven't done this in a while.
I thought you weren't a baby anymore.
Well, it's cold.
We'll be lonely again.
Not really. This time,
I can come back any time I want.
You're right. You can come
home any time you want.
I have no mother.
But I have a caring dad, a nosy old granny,
and a lively group of big sisters
to keep me company.
I can come home any time.
Thank you for waiting, Master Jinshi.
Please take care of our little girl.
We got her all dolled up for you.
Don't you forget, Maomao.
I know. Good customers, right?
Good. Now go on.
What a way to start the morning.
Let's go.
Uh, yeah.
Take care.
I'm off.
She's pretty.
Have you ever seen her at
the Verdigris House before?
This is your fault, Master Jinshi.
Hmm?
I got a lot of unwanted attention.
That's because you're...
What is it?
Nothing.
Good work. May we proceed?
Yes!
Apothecary. While you're here,
go back to your usual freckled face.
Huh?
Understood.
Hey, I heard the manager of the rear palace
bought out a courtesan
from the Verdigris House.
The Verdigris House? Is that where
the famous Three Princesses are?
The Verdigris House?
What is this guy doing?
And this is?
My house.
Huh?! Why?!
This is your new workplace.
Master Gaoshun, I was under the impression
we were returning to the rear palace...
We fired you once already, so we can't
just put you back in the same position.
You will be working in the outer court now.
The outer court...
Yes. The rear palace is
considered the inner court.
The outer court lies outside of that.
There are many public offices there.
I'll show you around later.
Welcome home. It must have been cold.
I am Suiren, his attendant.
You must be Xiaomao.
Y-Yes.
Xiaomao?
There are two separate buildings,
one with the office and one
with the personal residence.
The area ahead is the young
master's room, but...
"Young master?"
You should be all right.
This room's about the same size as
the one I used at the Jade Pavilion.
If this place had a stove and a nearby well...
Still, this place seems too well-built
for a servant girl's quarters.
Xiaomao?
Yes.
I don't intend to make you do servant labor.
Huh?
I told you, you're going to
work in the outer court.
You're going to take the court lady exam.
C-Court lady exam?!
A cotton garment? That's generous.
Good morning, Lady Suiren.
Oh, good morning, Xiaomao.
It's good that you wake up early.
I'll help.
It's fine, I'm almost done.
Can you just help serve?
Yes. Um, where are the other attendants?
There are none.
The office side is fine, but I couldn't let
anyone handle the personal side.
The young master's food is
especially out of the question.
So, you do all of this work by yourself?
We had some new girls a few times,
but well, things happen, and they don't last.
Did they lace his food with aphrodisiacs?
Or try to steal things?
I mean, who likes finding
unfamiliar underwear in their closet?
Huh?
On top of that, it was made of hair.
That sounds like a lot.
Yes, it certainly was.
Come, young master, please wake up.
It's time for breakfast.
So much wasted sex appeal...
I can see why only Master Gaoshun
and Lady Suiren enter this room.
A woman who saw this would lose herself easily.
A man would pounce on him right away.
He truly has a sin-inducing air about him.
Sort of like an insect in mating season.
I wonder if I could collect this eunuch's
scent and sell it as an aphrodisiac?
If you want, I can get you a new room.
What brings this about?
I don't get it, but is this my chance
to get a stove and well?!
He needs to tell me clearly
if he wants me to understand.
I can manage the stove somehow,
so for starters...
In that case, how about
a stable with a well nearby?
A stable.
Yes, a stable.
No stables.
So, shall we?
Yes, please.
Master Jinshi got left behind.
I assumed he had nothing to do, since
he was always loitering in the rear palace,
but he's actually pretty busy.
There are many military officers
on the east side of this area,
so please stay away if possible.
Understood.
The palace he showed me around was huge.
I needed more than all my fingers and toes
to count all the named buildings
and departments.
Can I learn them all?
My ability to learn about things
I'm not interested in is below average.
This is the Director of Waters.
It's the department in charge of rivers,
dams, and water utilization projects.
I see.
The rear palace had more medicinal ingredients.
My dad must have planted them
while he worked there.
Xiaomao, when you become a court lady,
the outer court will be your workplace.
Yes.
Court lady, huh?
Oh, good timing, Xiaomao.
Can you take this charcoal to the office?
Yes.
Excuse me.
So, this is Master Jinshi's office.
It's not extravagant,
but everything here is top class.
How high up is our young master?
Sizing up the new girl? Not a good atmosphere.
The court ladies of the outer court
are like secretaries.
They have the right qualifications,
background, and education.
They're nothing like the hodgepodge
of female officials at the rear palace.
Which explains their high self-esteem...
Hmm?
And therefore, they won't go out of their
way to clean, since that's not their job.
Just who do you think you are?
I guess they grow well when they're fed well.
Are you listening?!
Why is someone like you assigned
directly to Master Jinshi?!
I guess staying quiet would irritate them more.
In other words, you're all jealous of me?
Watch your mouth!
Wrong choice of words.
Fine, then.
Are you implying I'm getting
special treatment?
There's no way that could be right.
Why would he, a heavenly maiden
of a person, fall for an ugly girl like me?
Does the noble figure in your
mind have such bad taste?
Would he go out of his way
to eat meatless chicken bones,
when there are heaps of delicious abalones
and boar meat in front of him?
If that's the case, well, he must
have some interesting proclivities.
I don't really get it myself,
but does he truly have "special tastes"?
I see, so it's a "special taste"—
T-That's impossible!
R-Right!
Why did he hire you, then?
This is the reason.
I just tried out some burn
medicine the other day,
so it's really messed up right now.
Stings!
That heavenly maiden
has a heavenly heart, too.
He gives a person like me
a way to make a living.
Let's go.
Done and done.
"Interesting proclivities..."
Do you get harassed like that a lot?
Besides, why are you raising your left arm—
I'm off to my next cleaning duty.
Are you studying?
Sneak, sneak.
Hey!
Sneak, sneak!
Xiaomao.
Please be quiet.
And thus, the day of the exams came.
Why did you fail?
Why did you think I'd pass?
Maomao became Jinshi's personal servant.
What should we do?
What should we do, indeed?
Ow!
There shouldn't be any reason
for you to go beyond this point.
Could you say that before you hit me?
The scent of sandalwood, mixed
with another, distinctly bitter smell.
The military, huh?
Next Time
Next time: "The New
Pure Consort."
Episode 14: The New Pure Consort